Up everybody. Welcome to a brand new
episode of Part of the Problem. I've
been really looking forward to this one.
So, I'm glad you guys are tuning in.
It's going to be a good one. You know, I
had this experience uh recently. Uh I
was at an event, a libertarian event,
and someone said to me, I remember they
just said the the comment offhand, and
they they they were right in spirit, but
they were wrong technically. So, this is
good trivia to have. They said, "You
know, the craziest thing is that we
every American knows that we erected a
torture program and no one ever went to
jail for it." And I said, "That's not
true. That is not true. Someone did go
to jail for the the torture program that
the Bush administration um erected." And
of course, that is our guess. The person
who went to jail for it, of course, is
the person who exposed it to the
American people. And I think I this is
true for you. Um, this is true for uh
Bradley Manning, I guess later known as
Chelsea Manning. It's true for Julian
Assange. I think one of the things that
really has characterized where America
is at is that for all of the crimes that
have been committed just from the
government in the 21st century alone,
the people who end up get getting
punished are the ones who expose the
crimes rather than the people who
committed them. Of course, my guest for
today's show is John Kuryaku, who is a a
in my opinion an American hero. the CIA
[clears throat] whistleblower um uh who
who exposed the torture program during
the Bush administration. So, welcome,
sir. I'm sorry you have to hold the
distinct the distinct title of being the
only person to go to jail for the
torture program that was erected in this
country. Um but you've been well, you've
been a really valuable um a really
valuable contributor to this this
conversation and waking people up to the
nature of how government really works.
And so I'm I'm grateful for the work
that you do and I'm grateful that you
took some time to join us today.
>> Pleasure is all mine. Thanks for the
invitation.
>> Absolutely. You know, I was thinking I
was I was mentioning uh this to you just
before we got started, but there was I I
I knew we had booked this uh this
interview a few days ago and it was I
think the day before the UN Commission
on uh torture just came out with this
report that there was widespread um
torture going on over the I mean for
many years, but they say over the last
two years widespread torture of
Palestinians, many uh tortured to death.
Um, of course that did remind me of the
the torture programs that the United
States of America was involved in in the
uh wake in the immediate wake of 911 and
the war on terrorism. And then there was
this whole conversation that I was just
interviewed on Pierce Morgan about where
Netanyahu is claiming that um you know
he's he's requesting a pardon for his
corruption charges and he's claiming
that this is the path toward national
unity for Israel, right? like it's such
a divisive issue that half the country
wants me in jail and wouldn't it unify
everybody if we were to just give me a
pardon? And it just like the parallels
were so striking to me between Barack
Obama's position on not prosecuting Bush
error uh criminals which then of course
he ended up becoming one of but anyway
so so just curious your take on on all
of this the parallels between the
American uh dynamic and the Israeli
dynamic or what are you thinking this
week when you read about this stuff? Oh
my god. Where do you even begin with
something like that? You know what? Just
I'll I'll begin with a little a little
nit that has bothered me for a long
time. Uh it's when we talk about Israeli
hostages and Palestinian prisoners.
Why do we use different words to
describe people who have been snatched
off the street and not charged with a
crime? Why do the Israelis get to be
hostages and the Palestinians are
prisoners? They haven't been convicted
of anything. I was talking to a doctor
recently, an Israeli doctor, who's a
human rights activist, and he told me
that in in prison now, Palestinians are
not allowed to speak, number one, and
they're not allowed to walk. They have
to go from place to place like to the,
you know, food hall or whatever on all
fours. And it's just it's just to cow
them. So, you know, that's where do like
I say, where do you even begin? You
know, there are so many different things
we can talk about relative to torture
and things that we we know are wrong
because we're signitories to these
international conventions that ban, you
know, degrading and inhum inhumane
treatment and then we just pretend it
doesn't happen when we know it happens.
>> So, I I I don't get the double standard.
I've never understood the double
standard. This is not a partisan issue
because the Democrats and the
Republicans are equally guilty of doing
exactly this. Uh, you know, I was given
an interview earlier today and I said I
said that
that we're either going to be a country
that that is a shining beacon for human
rights and civil rights and civil
liberties or we're not. But we can't
pretend to be this great beacon of hope
and yell at other countries and tell
them how to conduct their business if
we're just going to be hypocrites about
it. And I'll give you I'll give you an
example.
When I was on on assignment to the State
Department, I was I was on rotation to
the State Department from 1994 to 1996.
I served in the American Embassy in
Bahrain as the economic um officer, but
I was also the human rights officer. And
so, you know, every year, every American
embassy in every country with which we
have diplomatic relations has to do a
human rights report and send it back to
to Congress. And so, that was part of my
job. I go out and interview attorneys
and and detainees and government
officials and everybody who has anything
to do with human rights. So when I go to
see the Minister of Interior and I say,
"Your Highness, you cannot pick up a
15-year-old boy off the street and beat
him to death because he marched in a
peaceful pro-democracy demonstration and
then call his parents that night, tell
him to come and pick up the body. You
can't do that. I have to report that to
Congress and they may cut off your arm
sales." But then an hour later,
some CIA guy comes in and says, "Don't
pay any attention to the human rights
guy. If we give you $10 million,
we want you to open up a secret torture
chamber and we're going to bring people
here, we'll disappear them, and you
torture them and then you give us a
transcript of what they say." What What
are they going to do? They going to
listen to John, the human rights guy.
>> Right. Right. or they going to listen to
the CIA guy with the suitcase full of
$10 million in cash.
>> So that's what we're up against.
>> Yeah. And it seems like there's there's
an interesting dynamic there where like
you also just in terms of public opinion
or something like that, like you just
lose the moral leg to stand on. You
know, you see, you know, there's uh I I
found this to be an interesting I' I've
mentioned this before on the show and
I'm really not even trying to beat up on
uh Joel Barry from the um he's he works
over at uh um what's it called? the not
the onion but the other one uh the
Babylon.
>> The Babylon bee. Yeah, there
>> Babylon be.
>> Yeah. So he So he said and like look I I
completely disagree with him on the
Israel stuff but like I agreed with them
I think on COVID and wokeism and and you
know they nothing against those guys
exactly but he said this to me at one
point is your first point here just
reminded me of this that I said when the
ceasefire had first uh broke out the the
latest ceasefire that is hanging on by a
thread over in Israel.
>> Yeah. If you could call that a
ceasefire, you know, like of course like
you know if if um Israel's killed I
think like maybe uh hundred or 200
civilians since the ceasefire has you
know like if if Palestinians had killed
200 Israeli civilians since then, we
wouldn't be considering this a
ceasefire. But I said something at the
very beginning of the ceasefire. I had a
very generic tweet I thought that was
just like hey hope this works. I'm not
optimistic but let's hope something
better comes. And I said at least I said
at the very least at least there's
prisoner swaps. Uh or I said there's
hostage swaps going on and there's more
aid getting in right now than there was
a few weeks ago. So that's better. And
then Joel Barry got very offended. He
goes, "How dare you call them hostage
swaps? One side is all innocent Israelis
and the other side is all a bunch of
terrorists." And I just thought this was
such an amazing moment because like
first of all, look, dude, it it's just
the way people conceive of these things.
And then it's circular. Yeah. If your
starting point is that all the Israelis
are angels and all the Palestinians are
terrorists, well then sure. But there
were IDF soldiers who were amongst the
hostages and there were 1,700 people who
had never been charged with anything who
Israel was holding. So literally one one
is a look again all these things are
complicated. I don't ever want to see
prisoners of war or hostages even when
they're soldiers. But like it's a
different thing for an IDF soldier to be
being held in occupied territory than it
is for just some Palestinian
boy who was never charged with anything
to get tortured.
>> I gave an interview I'm going to say
four or five weeks ago and I said and
and and slap me if this is too
controversial but I said I believed that
both sides should respect the basic
tenants of human rights. Next thing I
know, I have a Google alert on myself
just to see what people are saying if I
need to defend myself or whatever.
There's uh there's an article in some
obscure uh Middle Eastern journal and
it's written by the political director
in the Israeli foreign minister's office
and he says John Kiryaku, a noted
anti-semite,
said blah blah blah that we should
respect human rights. I'm like what? I
said, "Listen, people have called me a
lot of things over the years. A noted
anti-semite is not one of them because I
said that both sides should respect
human rights."
>> Incredible.
>> And I'll tell you the truth, I have a
lot of friends who are either Israeli or
Israeli American. There's one one friend
I'm particularly close to who who's
served several years in the IDF. And I
said, "Dude," I said, "Check me if I
become,
you know, if I say things that are a
little too too far over in the way of
human rights." And he said, "I'd be the
first to check you." And no, you haven't
said anything.
>> Well, it's it's, you know, they they got
this Zoran mom, Donnie, who's the the
mayor elect of New York City here now,
first of all, is I mean, he was like a
woke democratic socialist. He he's got
like in my opinion some of the like
cringiest and most ridiculous opinions
ever. But the thing they tried the thing
they tried to get him on John was that
he said he had this hilarian statement
where he said that I think Israel should
be a state with equal rights for
everybody. Imagine and
>> this is and they try imagine trying to
turn that statement into some type of
like hateful and they actually used it
like they played the clip of it and went
listen to him when they say does Israel
have a right to exist and he goes yeah
and he goes Israel have a right to exist
as a Jewish state and he goes they have
a right to exist as a state with equal
rights for everyone and they're like the
horror what exactly are you talking
about
>> exactly and then when they deny when
they deny that there are similarities
between Israel today and South Africa in
the 1980s and then they confuse which
one you're talking about.
>> Yeah.
>> I mean, come on, man. It's an
indictment.
>> But there are a lot of Let me add one
other one other thought. This is
something that's really been bothering
me a lot lately is here in the United
States. Um
>> I listen, I have friends completely
across the ideological spectrum. I genu
genuinely don't care if people are
Democrats or Republicans or
conservatives or it makes no difference
to me. I think we can we can find common
ground on everything. But I can't tell
you how many friends that I have from
both the left and the right who have
said after I say something like, you
know, there should be an investigation
on human rights abuses. And they'll say,
I didn't know you were pro- Hamas. It's
like, what the [__] are you talking
about? Pro- Hamas, are you kidding me? I
was on Pierce Morgan one time and um and
I like going I actually was on Pierce
Morgan, let me look, 15 minutes ago, but
I was on several months ago and
funny thing to me is he he had me as one
of the right-wing guys, uh which it only
occurred to me 20 minutes into the show.
Uh but, uh he said to me, "Do you
believe that Hamas is a terrorist
organization?" I said, "Of course." And
he said, "Was October 7th a a terrorist
attack?" And I said, "Of course it was."
And he said, "So what is the point that
that you're holding to here?" And I
said, "The point I'm holding to is that
Israel has to respect human rights. It
really is as simple as that." And he
says, "Anybody disagree?" And everybody
on the panel agreed. And then Pierce
says, "I think this is the first time
we've ever talked about Israel on this
show." And all four panelists agreed.
I mean, what's so hard about that?
>> All right, guys. Let's take a moment and
thank our sponsor for today's show,
which is Calshi. We've been telling you
about them for a while, and they've been
popping up all over the place. As I'm
sure you guys know by now, Kelsey is the
first ever fully regulated CFTC
approved, available in all 50 states
prediction market. So, basically, you
can bet on anything that's got a clear
outcome. You can bet on whether
inflation will go up or down next year.
where you can bet on who's going to win
the midterm elections, who's going to be
the next president, but you can also
view it as a prediction market and see
where people are putting their money.
So, it's very interesting. It kind of
keeps your finger on the pulse of
American culture and also you can throw
some money down and win. Cali.com/dave.
Go check out Kshi today. Check out the
markets. Get in on the betting. Have
some fun. Let's get back into the show.
Yeah. Well, it's I you know I again like
you said before when you're you know
when there are these terms that are used
like um like hostage verse prisoner
>> but really there is no definitional
difference between the two things. I
mean especially when you're talking
about the the only difference really is
whether it's state or non-state actors
like whether it's a non-state actor
taking somebody or it's a state actor
taking someone. If you never gave him a
trial or anything even resembling a
military tribunal, then you're the same.
You're a guy with a gun who snatched
somebody and is keeping them in
captivity. But then here's the same the
same thing is that that also applies to
this term terrorism. And I know that you
know you you are somebody who has a
career in counterterrorism and I but
like you said before, I'm I'm not a
lefty at all. I'm a hardcore
libertarian. But [clears throat] Nam
Chomsky, man, he really did nail it when
he said he goes, "Fundamentally, what is
the difference between terrorism and
counterterrorism? It's terrorism when
they do it and it's counterterrorism
when we do it." And that's really the
only difference. And so I I mean, I told
a spokesman for the IDF on Pierce Morgan
the other day, he said something that he
didn't respect my line of inquiry. And I
said I said, "Sir, you're the spokesman
for a terrorist organization."
And I think I tried to make it a funny
line. And I said, "You're a spokesman
for the biggest terror uh terrorist
organization in a region known for
terrorist organizations." [laughter] And
but it really that is it. And I think
that this is just it's it's gotten to a
point where I think that what's kind of
interesting is it seems to me like you
were a guy who kind of woke up to the
reality of this on the inside
>> and then in the in the following two
decades it seems like the people have
woken up to this reality from the
outside.
>> Oh, I'll give you I'll give you an
example. I'm sorry to interrupt you.
>> Oh, no. Go ahead. The
>> the night that we captured Abu Zuba and
dozens and dozens of other al-Qaeda
fighters, um we caught so many people
that night that we had to bring them
into our safe house for interrogation in
shifts. We had to bring them in 10 at a
time in a patty wagon. So the first
group comes in and there was this idiot
working for me. He had flown out to
Pakistan just for the operation, but he
was a total [__] and thought he was in
charge and I had to slap him down a
couple of times. So he brings these
prisoners in and they all have bags on
their heads. And I said, "Why do they
have hoods on?" And he said, "We don't
want them to see our our faces." And I
said, "Are you seriously telling me that
you have never read the Geneva
Convention? It is a war crime to put
hoods on them." I said, "Take the hoods
off." And he goes, "Wait."
And he says, "Don't take the hoods off."
And he says to me, "I'm going to report
you to headquarters." And I said, "Oh,
I'm already reporting you to
headquarters for committing a war crime.
Take the hoods off." And they took the
hoods off. We reported each other to
headquarters. I got reprimanded.
Yeah. Well, it really does show you um
that which is kind of a a you know,
libertarian view of mine that the thing
about the law is that there's really no
such thing. And it's a nice idea, but
they are after all words written down on
a piece of paper. And you know, like you
you see this all the time like uh
there'll be like videos um like police
arrest videos and there's always you
find that one you know the sovereign
citizen or whoever who's like I know my
rights and you know then you you watch
the cops like mhm get out of the car and
they're like I have the right not to get
out of the car. Then the cop breaks the
windows out of the car.
>> I watch those every single night. Well,
what's so [laughter] I think what's so
fascinating about them, John, is that
you actually when you watch it, what
you're actually watching is this this
confrontation between um abstract
conceptions
and brutal reality. And in a sense, like
you got a man with a gun who's got a
walkie-talkie to a bunch of other men
with guns. you are outgunned and
outmanned by the most powerful gang in
the land, which is the local police in
any jurisdiction in the United States of
America. But then in your mind, you're
like, "Yes, but something was written
down on a scroll in the late 1700s and I
believe that hocus pocus this undo."
Like it is almost a belief in magic.
What you realize is that the law is at
the end of the day whatever is enforced.
If you're in a 60 mile per hour speed
limit, but they don't pull you over
unless you go 75, then the speed limit
is 75 miles per hour in reality. And I
think what you're what you're describing
there is that in reality, war crimes
aren't illegal, but reporting on them
is.
>> That is that is the sad sorry state that
we find ourselves in. You're absolutely
right.
>> Yeah. So So as you now you're So you
were at the CIA before 911.
>> Oh, yeah. I was at the CIA what 11 years
before 911.
>> Okay. So you came in 1990. So 1990 to
around 2006.
>> Uh there 2005. Yeah.
>> 2005. Sorry. Uh so now I know you've
talked about this before but you that's
that to me is a very interesting dynamic
because not only obviously um the
you know the nature of the CIA has been
something different than what the
American people have understood of it
for a long time but obviously things
really changed after 911 and the war on
terror launched. I also I also feel like
there's I mean like I remember you know
like my my parents were interested in
politics. um that Crossfire was on my my
living room in the 90s or something like
that. And I think if you had asked them,
they would have said that um you know,
yeah, there's a CIA and they do secret
spy stuff. Sure, they probably even knew
they were toppling some communist
governments or something like that
around the world, but I don't think when
they looked at politics, they ever
thought this is a show orchestrated by
the deep state that is irrelevant to the
real mechanisms of government that the
deep state is actually running this
thing. Whereas now, I think that's like
common knowledge amongst the American
people. Yet you're so you I want like
from your perspective, you're in the
CIA. you go in there believing in the
cause, believing you're serving your
country. What was like what what were
the steps of where you started going
like, "Oh man, this might be something
really unsavory that I'm a part of."
>> You know, the first
>> the first time I ever considered the
notion of a deep state. I still remember
it. I It was an It was one specific
meeting. There is uh there's a group at
that's housed at the CIA called the
National Intelligence Council. So
they're supposed to be the topmost
analysts from all around the
intelligence community. These are the
best and the brightest, right? They're
all in the senior intelligence service.
Almost all of them have PhDs. Sometimes
they go back and forth between the CIA
and Harvard and Stanford and places like
that. And there was one guy who was the
NIO, the national intelligence officer
for warning. So, he's supposed to be the
guy that's looking 5, 10, 20 years down
the line saying, you know, I think that
Bolivia is going to be a problem for us
20 years from now.
Well, I remember going into this meeting
with him and I was a young kid. I was in
my 20s. He was an old man, but
everybody, you know, 50 and older in my
mind was an old man at the time. I'm 61
now and I realize how foolish that was.
But [laughter] anyway, people were
congratulating him and I asked somebody.
I said, "Why is everybody congratulating
him?" "Oh, he got an age waiver from the
director." And I said, "What's that
mean?" "Oh, he's allowed to work until
he's 70." I was like, "7? How old is he
now?" He's 65. He's been in this job for
42 years, and he's going to stay for
another five years. And I was like, why
would anybody want to want to be in a
job for for 47 years, the same job?
Well, because that's the power that
you've built. That's the authority that
you've built. Presidents come and go.
How many presidents are going to come
and go over the course of this guy's
47year CIA career. So, he knows that if
the president calls and says, "Listen, I
want you to take a really hard look at,
you know, Brazil."
He can tell the president go screw
himself. Not in so many words,
>> right?
>> But he can just so so slow roll this
response that by the time he feels like
getting around to it, the president's
long gone. And I realized for the very
first time there actually is a deep
state. We can call it the state.
>> We can call it the federal bureaucracy,
but by God it's there. It exists,
>> you know. Uh so it reminds me as you say
this uh so there's this really great
book uh written by Hans Herman Hapa it's
called Democracy the God that failed and
it's it's essentially a right-wing
libertarian critique of democracy and
but whether whether you come away like
completely agreeing with his thesis or
not it's just a it's a worthwhile read.
It's a very fascinating like right-wing
libertarian critique on democracy. And
essentially, if I could boil it down,
like his argument is basically that like
the having democracy essentially makes
the government like it like publicly
owned. And the way if we think about the
way any piece of property is owned, we
all on some level we all know that like
um owners take better care of a house
than renters. You know, like it's just
if you if it's your problem that you're
gonna have to deal I know this just from
like I own a house now and I used to
rent a house now. When I own the house
I'm thinking about like oh well what's
best for in 20 years? What's when you're
renting you're just not you're like
what's going to am I going to get my
security deposit back is essentially
your concern. [laughter]
>> And so bas essentially his point was
that he was going like well look hey
people who believe in free markets
people who believe in capitalism we all
recognize that everything is better
owned privately. And the logical
conclusion of that is kind of like if
you're going to have a government,
you're better off having just a decision
maker at the top rather than this thing
where essentially you're in for four
years, you're you're only incentives are
to loot as much out of it as you can
before you get out. But then I think
another aspect is what you're talking
about. In a sense, I'm not just sticking
up for the deep state, but in a sense
there you're going, well, hey, what are
they going to do? They are the permanent
part of the government after after all.
You know, like after all, the CIA is
going to be making decisions. The CIA
has been making important decisions
since it was created. We've had dozens
of presidents since then, but we have
not had or I guess do the math,
whatever, since the end of World War II.
But the point is there's been a whole
lot of them coming in and going. And so
almost just by the nature of the system,
it's almost designed that of course the
intelligence agencies would have to
think like that, to think like, yeah,
whatever. Trump's going to come in and
have his whole executive order tariffs.
Okay. Then the next guy gets in there
and he can undo all of them. So, who
cares,
>> right? Yeah. That's what it comes down
to.
>> Yeah.
>> So, do you Sorry. Go ahead.
>> I was going to say and for a minute we
thought that oversight committees might
might fix that. And I chuckle about it
now. At the time, 1975, 1976, this this
seemed like a good idea that the the
deep state has become too big, too
powerful, too widespread. It kills
anybody that gets in their way. They
experiment on Americans, you know,
dosing people with LSD, forcing people
to jump out of windows. We got to put a
hold on this. And that lasted for what,
six years,
until we decided, ah, no, you know what?
We're going to sell weapons to the
Iranians, which is illegal, and then
we're going to have a Saudi middleman do
it, and he'll launder the money for us.
Then we'll use the money to buy new
weapons that we're going to use this guy
in Cyprus to send to the rebels in
Nicaragua, which is also illegal, and
just hope that nobody notices.
>> Yeah. And and and also like just to add
into that um that the it was already
known that the position of the
administration was supporting Saddam
Hussein in that war. So the
administration is supporting the other
side of the war. Like I I mean it's just
it's un I always find that to be uh I
just love that that example in American
history, the the Iraq Iran war of 1980
to 1986 just because like it's so
indefensible to fund both sides of a
war. Like it's almost like it's it's
almost even more indefensible than just
launching a war of aggression because at
least launching a war of aggression, you
know, you can claim some preemptive like
well we felt that we would we had to do
this or something else would happen. But
when you're funding both sides of a war,
you go, "Oh, you're just a monster."
>> Oh my god. And it was even worse than
that. As soon as one would get a leg up
on the other, we would increase the
level of intelligence cooperation. So if
the Iranians move into Iraqi territory,
then we start giving the Iraqis top
secret overhead imagery. And then if the
Iraqis push into Iranian territory, then
we start giving the Iranians overhead
imagery.
>> So it was hideous.
>> That I didn't know. That's really
interesting. So when you say the period
where like there were six, you're saying
like after the church hearings, but
before like the not I don't know what
you would call it, but before the the
Carter doctrine and then the Reagan
doctrine in the Middle East. So like we
had a little period there where the CIA
wasn't people.
>> Yeah. This little period. Exactly. Yeah.
And then, you know, there was kind of a
golden a golden age very briefly uh
under under Bill Clinton where where
Clinton came down with this edict that
he did not want the CIA to do anything
with anybody that had what he called a
human rights problem. So, if you were a
recruited asset of the CIA and oh, by
the way, you happen to run this Honduran
death squad, uh you're fired. We use the
word terminated at the CIA, but people
would take that wrong. So, you're fired.
There's no more paycheck. There's no
more cooperation. And I remember people
laughing when that first came down. And
then as it was implemented, people were
like, "Oh, oh, he's serious. This is
actually working out. Okay. Well, good
for us." And then 911 happened. And I
said earlier in an interview, the
pendulum tends to swing both ways. Well,
it went so far after 911 that it's not
yet swung back. All right, guys. Let's
take a moment and thank our sponsor for
today's show, which is Brunt Work Wear.
These are the most comfortable pair of
work boots I have ever put on my
delicate feet. I highly recommend them.
It is the holiday season. If you're
looking for a gift for a hardworking guy
or gal in your life, definitely go check
out Brunt Workware. Traditionally
speaking, we all know if you wanted a
good pair of work boots, they were going
to be uncomfortable as hell, at least
for the first six months that you wear
them. You could either have a nice
comfortable pair of sneakers or you
could have a good pair of work boots.
But that dynamic no longer exists thanks
to Brunt. They have made the most
comfortable pair of work boots that you
will ever own. And with temperatures
dropping and the holidays coming up,
everybody could use a new pair of work
boots. This is where you go to get them.
And our listeners will get $10 off if
they use the promo code problem when
they go to bruntwork.com.
That's bruntwork.com.
Promo code problem for $10 off the most
comfortable, durable pair of work boots
you will ever own. All right, let's get
back into the show.
>> Yeah. Yeah, that's right. So, what Yeah.
Well, Bill Clinton had some good ideas
and then all of a sudden he's in a blue
dress on Jeffrey Estein's living room
wall or something. Um, so was [laughter]
was your because I want to ask a bunch
about this because this is like a a
topic that I'm I've been very fascinated
with and read a lot about, but you were
there. So there the the neoconservatives
who of course were like whatever. There
was like the origins in team B in the
their intellectuals. They had positions
in the Reagan administration and in the
George HW Bush administration, but
during those Clinton years that you're
talking about, they're essentially out
of power.
And a lot of them were Democrats,
believe it or not. Like Richard Pearl
never changed his voter registration
from Democrat to Republican. And a lot
of them as Yeah. A lot of them as very
young men worked for Scoop Jackson
>> who was a Democratic senator from
Washington State.
>> No, that I did know. I mean, they were
Troskyites into Democrats then into
that's why they were the neo
conservatives. Right. Right. So this now
these guys while they're out obviously
they they have made cozy relationships
with the military-industrial complex at
this point like in the 90s all those
Bill Crystal think tanks are funded by
weapons companies and they are
advocating um
>> both to Benjamin Netanyahu and then
later to uh Bill Clinton that we go
overthrow Saddam Hussein that we attack
Iran attack Syria before 9/11. So
there's 10 months before 9/11 where like
George W. Bush is in and he's staffed
his administration with all these
neocons. What was the feeling then? Like
cuz weren't weren't they from my
understanding is they were kind of
viewed as the crazies in the basement.
There's this group of war hawks that
always wants to blow everything up but
like whatever they don't really have any
power. There was in even in the George
HW Bush, there were Brent Skras and
there were people who could like veto
them who are like they're not going to
get all their craziest views through.
But like I'm saying before 911 in the
Bush administration, you guys must have
noticed like, oh man, Dick Cheney just
staffed the entire government with these
guys at the most powerful positions
>> and as their deputies and deputies
deputies. I'll tell you a funny story.
When I was in Bahrain from 94 to 96, I
had an intern working for me and he was
a student at Yale. He was a sophomore at
Yale. Really, really smart guy.
and we kind of sort of stayed in touch
in the years after. He he stayed at Yale
and got a masters. Then he got a PhD
and then he sent me a note saying, "Hey,
um I just got a job at the Pentagon uh
working in this new um under secretariat
for intelligence." And I said, "Oh,
cool." I said, "Why don't you come over
to the agency? I'm working for the
deputy director and you can brief him
on, you know, what the Pentagon's
thoughts are on Iraq. He comes over,
gives this briefing and I remember being
like appalled and my boss kept looking
at me like, "What are you doing bringing
this guy here?" So I walked him out to
his car and I said, "Michael, I have to
ask you, when did you become a fascist?"
And he turned to me and he says, "We're
in charge now. we're in charge and
Saddam Hussein's going to die.
And I was like, "Oh my god." Well, he's
working for he's working for well, I I
don't want to name names, but he's
working for all those guys at the
Pentagon who later became famous and
appeared in Vanity Fair and these
exposees about, you know, how we ended
up at war in Iraq. It turns out that
they just they just beded their time
knowing that they had a champion in Dick
Cheney, that Dick Cheney was the one
running the show. You know, it's funny
because right before 911 at the CIA, it
was China, China, China, China. And I
was working in the counterterrorism
center at the time and I was like, ah,
you know, they really should kind of
divert some of their attention away from
China and start looking at this this
terrorism situation in the Middle East.
But it was all about China. And then
once we got hit, I mean, listen, there's
this famous story that Richard Pearl was
at the White House on September 12th,
2001 and said, you know, we have to
attack Iraq, right? And then it was just
history from there.
So now now I know I I've made a lot out
of this o over years and I think you've
you've given me you know from other
interviews of yours that I've I've
watched like you've given me some of the
information um about this that I've I've
had people who have tried to like debunk
this but I just find the case to be
pretty overwhelming. But if you look at
say just just to pick some like public
writings, okay, Benjamin Netanyahu
writes a book in '95 or '96 called
Fighting Terrorism that kind of lays a
lot of this stuff out. In 1996, is also
when Richard Pearl and David Worms and
Douglas fight write the clean break memo
to Benjamin Netanyahu. The same year,
1996, David Worms writes a companion
piece called Coping with Crumbling
States. Now, anybody can go read this
stuff. It's all out there uh public. I
mean, you might have to buy Benjamin
Netanyahu's book, but the rest of them
are all up in PDFs for free on the
internet. And they're very clear that
their plan is to explicitly to get away
from the peace process and the promise
of Oslo, which is to give the
Palestinians their own states. And
instead, what the Israelis need to do is
reverse the Yeetsak Rabin doctrine,
which was we have to make peace with the
Palestinians in order to make peace with
the broader Arab world. And they go,
"No, no, no, no. We're going to do the
opposite. we're going to overthrow all
the problematic regimes in the broader
Arab world or broader Muslim world and
that way we never have to make peace
with the Palestinian. We never have to
do a land for peace deal. Now this this
in in um the uh the uh the clean break
memo they specifically called for
overthrowing Saddam Hussein uh strikes
on Iran, strikes on Syria. Then we have
um the um obviously the letters to Bill
Clinton urging him to overthrow uh
Saddam Hussein 98 I believe. Then you
have um uh General Wesley Clark's now
famous comments about how the plan was
to overthrow seven uh countries in the
next five years. By the way, those se of
those seven countries,
>> six of them for sure have been attacked
by either Israel, the United States, or
both since the seventh one, Sudan. The
the king died. There was a civil war. It
was broken up. I they believe there's
still a horrible conflict going on over
there.
>> A genuine civil war taking place right
now.
>> Yes. It's really awful. Um, and so now
and and I don't know the exact details,
but I know there's all types of George
Soros uh like articles about how Sudan
needs to be separated and needed to be,
you know, uh um southern Sudan needed to
be removed. So, I don't know exactly the
details of the intervention there, but
there's now when people try to argue
with this a lot of times they'll say,
"Okay, but the clean break memo didn't
happen exact like it didn't happen
exactly the way it's written because
they said they wanted a Hashemite king
to come in. Okay, the Hashimite king
died. Chalabe was the one who sold him
on the whole Hashmite King thing.
Anyway, they basically went with the
same version of that of Chalabe's group
uh supposedly taking over. Now, now
again, I guess the point that I've
always been making with all this stuff
when you put it together is that clearly
like for the same reason that people
read foreign affairs because they want
to get the thinking in Washington. So
clearly the thinking in Washington here
is that we are going to fight multiple
regime change wars of choice and like
that this this had been a plan. It
really got animated after 911. Now you
had some interesting information on this
too where you had you had explicitly
heard tell me remind me of this. Who did
you hear from that we would be in tan by
next year and this was in 2001 I think
you had heard this?
>> Uh it was in two it was in February of
2003.
>> Oh okay my mistake.
>> So this is this is the night before we
attack Iraq. Um, I was the notetaker in
a meeting that is called a principal
committee meeting. So, it's normally
chaired by the president. In this case,
for whatever reason, it was chaired by
Vice President Cheney. But I'm sitting
in the CIA director's conference room
with George Tennant. He's the only
person sitting at the table. I'm sitting
directly behind him to take notes. And
the Cheney is on one screen sharing the
meeting. Condi Rice is next to him on
the next screen. And Colin Pal's on the
screen. and um and Secretary um Rumsfeld
is on a screen and and there are a
couple of NSC senior directors and then
the head of um Sentcom, Sincent,
commander-in-chief of Central Command,
General who is that Tommy Franks. And so
I've always hated the Order of Battle
Briefings. I've always hated them
because I don't understand them and I
just don't give a [__] where we have,
you know. So anyway, Cheney starts by
saying, "General Franks, why don't you
start off with the order of battle
briefing?" And I was like, "Ugh." So I'm
I'm ready to write it down. He's like,
"You know, elements of the first army
division are at this location and the
fifth cavalry brigade is here and
they're moving north at 20 kilometers
and I don't care where these guys are."
So he finishes the briefing and he says,
"If all go if all goes as planned, we
can be in Tehran by August." And George
very discreetly reaches in front of him
and and turns off the microphone. And
then he turns to me and he says, "Did he
say Thran or did he say Baghdad?"
And I said, "He said Thran."
And George says, "Have they lost their
minds?" And then he discreetly turns the
microphone back on and just kind of sits
there for the rest of the briefing. I go
down to um back to my office afterwards,
I should say. At the very end of the
briefing, this idiot who was a senior
director at the NSC
um says excitedly as everybody's, you
know, getting up and they're logging
off, he says, when we cross that border
tomorrow morning, they're going to throw
flowers at us. And I remember thinking,
do they know nothing about history? Like
they they they must know nothing about
the history of the Middle East. So I go
back to the office, my boss says, how
was the briefing? And I said, "Did you
know we were going to attack Iran?"
And he goes, "Are they still talking
about that? We're not going to attack
Iran." And I said, "These guys know
nothing about history." He said, "Of
course they don't know anything about
history. That's why they think we're
going to go to go to Iran. We're not
going to go to Iran."
And then, you know, we attacked Iraq the
next day and everything turned to [__]
after that.
>> Right. Right. And of course you could
see where it at least it seems to me um
that amongst that neoconservative group
and and of course you never know what's
in everybody's hearts and minds and
stuff but it does seem like they
believed it like that they really did
believe that I mean listen I saw I saw
an interview with David Worms from a few
weeks ago a few weeks ago and the clean
break memo gets brought up and he starts
defending it how yes if you had put the
Hasheite king in Iraq that the Shiites
would have had to listen to the
Hashemites and therefore they would have
told the Lebanese to knock it off and be
friendly with Israel. Like it does seem
like they and and it's hard I think for
younger people to understand I I guess
because I was alive in the 80s and 90s I
kind like I think there was a feeling
particularly after the first Persian
Gulf War where it was like in the
unipolar moment like this is America. If
we want to topple Saddam's regime we'll
topple them immediately. we'll we'll
move on to Tyrron next year and then
like whoopsie, nobody saw like a civil
war where a million people get killed
breaking out and the whole thing being a
catastrophe. But it at least seems to me
that like those people were actually
that stupid. Yes, they were actually
that ignorant of history and thought we
were going to be greeted as liberators.
>> Willful blindness really is is what it
was. Like how could you not think that
two million people are going to end up
dead by the time you decide to finally
leave?
>> Yeah. Like how could you conclude
anything other than this is going to be
a disaster and millions of people are
going to die? And on top of it all,
Saddam Hussein,
like him or hate him, like his politics
or hate his politics, was literally the
only Sunni bull work against Iran. And
if if you're you know the king of
Bahrain or the Amir of Kuwait or the
king of Saudi Arabia and your population
is small and you're petrified of Iranian
expansionism, the only thing that's
going to protect you is a Sunni leader
in Iraq. When I first started as an
analyst, um I I was an analyst on Iraq
for the whole first, you know, seven or
eight years of my career. And our
analytic line was that yeah, Iraqis
would probably be very happy to see
Saddam go, but they would also be very
happy to see him pl replaced by a Sunni
military huta, right? where there's no
clear person in charge, but it's a bunch
of Sunni generals who are going to keep
the Iranians off everybody's back, but
are going to allow some degree of
freedom and respect for human rights
among the populace. And that never
happened,
>> right? All right, guys. Let's take a
moment and thank our sponsor for today's
show, which is Hexclad. The holiday
season is here, and let's be real, the
kitchen is where it all goes down. big
feasts, family hanging out, everybody
having a good time. But what you need is
to have your cookware game up to par,
and that's where Hexclad comes in. I
will tell you something, they uh sent me
over a couple different pounds, a couple
pots. I got their steel Damascus knives.
My wife loves them. Uh we use these in
my household, so I can really recommend
them. Check them out. This is the
ultimate gift for yourself or to anyone
in your life who wants to level up their
kitchen game. And these are pieces that
are really going to be the last pots and
pans you have to buy, the last knives
you have to buy. They're all very high
quality and they are backed with a
lifetime warranty. So, this set is the
last set of cookware you're ever going
to need to buy. Go check them out right
now. And you can also get 10% off if you
go to hexcloud.com/pro.
That's excl.com/pro
for 10% off your order. Seriously, this
is a great Christmas gift either to
yourself or to someone you love.
hexclad.com/pros.
Let's get back into the show. Right. So,
do you now what what was your take like
in those days about the relationship
that Israel had with all of this? Um
because obviously I you know I I think
sometimes almost like this this debate
it like gets into semantics you know
people will be like you know was it
Israel's war? Was it our war? Like
obviously it's much more complicated
than that. And I think that the
essentially the Israeli government and
the US government have so merged
especially on like the deep state level
that it's almost like hard to tell where
one stops and the other one begins. But
there's kind of no question here that
like okay the neoconservatives
obviously like I just said they're
writing these letters to Benjamin
Netanyahu. They're they're clearly
married at the hip with the lood party.
Obviously the Israel lobby was very
instrumental. the neoonservatives
themselves are a part of the Israel
lobby. Like obviously this was all very
instrumental and the feeling I guess was
right like that this will make the
region safer for Israel or something
like that. Like what was your
perspective on the inside of how much of
a role that or how much of an influence
that was playing?
>> Well, the first Gulf War was crystal
clear. Uh Iraq invaded Kuwait. Saddam
miscalculated. Thought that certainly
the United States wouldn't go to
Kuwait's aid. We didn't have very good
relations with Kuwait at the time. they
were members of the non-aligned uh
movement and we you know we had an
embassy there but we weren't terribly
close friends. Um he was wrong. The the
Iraq war was an entirely different
animal. Uh the Israelis begged us to let
them join in the attack on Iraq and
everybody they approached whether it was
at the Pentagon or the White House or
the CIA said absolutely not. Now they
tried to get a couple of shots in. I I
won't say more than that, but they tried
to get a couple of shots in on the day
that we crossed the border. Uh but they
they were so excited as as to the point
of giddiness that they wanted to be
involved in this war and and the
overthrow of Saddam Hussein.
You make an important point here that I
want to amplify. It's not that our
relations
coincided.
It's that the Israelis along with the
neocons had been working on the
government so consistently since the
middle of the Clinton administration,
since the beginning of the Clinton
administration that there was just
almost no way out of it. Like in
retrospect, of course we attacked Iraq.
I mean, even if we hadn't made up the
whole notion of of weapons of mass
destruction, we would have made up
something else to justify an attack on
Iraq. I mean, look at Dick Cheny's
efforts to connect Saddam Hussein with
al-Qaeda.
For those of us inside the CIA who knew
a little bit about Iraq and about
al-Qaeda and about Islam,
I mean, everybody to a man would have
said there's literally nothing Muslim
about Saddam Hussein. He famously made
the Umra, the minor pilgrimage to Saudi
Arabia and it was either 1987 or 1988.
He went with the vice president of Iraq,
Isat Ibraim. Is that Ibrahim was a pious
Sufi Muslim.
Saddam didn't even know the prayers. And
so when they went to the Cabba to pray,
um, is that Ibrahim knelt just behind
Saddam to whisper the prayers to him so
that he could say them out loud and make
it look like he knew what the hell he
was doing. So there was no connection
between al-Qaeda and Saddam Hussein.
Osama bin Laden hated Saddam Hussein at
least as much as he hated the United
States. There was no connection there.
But Dick Cheney counted correctly, as it
turned out, on the American people being
so stupid and so gullible that they
would just go along with it.
>> Yeah. Well, I guess I and and I don't
have the expertise you have, but I do
know enough to know when you see a
French beret on someone, that's not a
sign of an Islamist. That's usually not
the first sign. You don't have to know
that much [laughter] to know that that's
probably not what you're dealing with.
No, I mean it's unbel throughout the
whole thing. And I remember um just I I
remember watching like Carl Rove on Bill
O'Reilly, you know, during those years
come in and he would look they they
would do this because they were they
were good at this because he never
explicitly, you know, like lied,
>> but he would so play on the ignorance of
the Fox News audience that he would say
things, you know, in the context of this
is 2005 or something like that and he
would say Iran is the biggest thunder of
terrorism and like in an immediate post
911 world. You know that every Fox News
viewer when they hear that is hearing,
"Oh, you mean the guys who took down
these towers? I know the Durka Derka
Muslim terrorists. Those are the guys
who took our towers down." Now, he just
omits that like, "Oh, actually there are
these shirts and skins over there and
they're different sides and like they're
on the other side. They're actually at
war with the terrorists who we have a
problem with." And so there was this
constant attempt to like play on the
ignorance of the American population and
then mislead them toward thinking that
there, you know, like now again like
they they maybe never technically said,
you know, Iran was involved in 911 and
they really hinted at Saddam Hussein
being involved, but they totally just
gave that impression to the American
people that that's what's going on here.
>> 100% right. That's exactly what they
did. They tricked the American people
into buying into this nonsense. You
know, I there's something happening
right now, too. And I've noticed this on
I've noticed this on Fox News and
elsewhere in the in the right-wing print
media. Uh it's about the Muslim
Brotherhood in Egypt. And in fact, I
think I'm not positive. I think the
State Department has just declared the
Muslim Brotherhood a terrorist
organization or elements of it a
terrorist organization.
The Muslim Brotherhood has never ever
carried out an anti-American terrorist
uh operation. And in fact, I mean, it's
a it's 105 years old and has never ever
been called a terrorist organization by
any American administration. It's
fundamentalist.
It doesn't like us, but that doesn't
mean it's a terrorist organization,
>> right?
>> So, what do we do now? It's going to be
a terrorist organization. Does that mean
we attack it?
>> Like, what what's the reason for for
making this declaration?
>> I don't understand. Well, well, it's
another thing that seems to be uh going
on with this new term that I It's
amazing how these new terms come out and
then all of a sudden every like uh
pro-war right-winger is repeating them.
But narco terrorist is the new term now
in Venezuela where like what exactly the
hell does narco terrorist even mean?
Like do you get the terrorist label like
okay so they've they've killed civilians
in an attempt to shift politics. No,
that's not what we're claiming at all.
where there were drugs on a boat. Maybe
like we haven't actually demonstrated
that or proved it. But it is amazing how
essentially terrorists became this label
to like shut off your brain and shut off
your conception of rights or laws of war
or due process or anything like that.
And then I literally heard the just the
other day where someone uh uh was saying
I don't wait this double tap strike on
this vote. It's like why' you have to
come back and kill the wounded people
who were taken out of action already?
And then the next response is, "Oh, what
are you defending? Narco terrorists."
Exactly. Turn your brain off and just
don't even think about this.
>> Yeah. Just just stunning. You know, it's
it's so easy to forget that there are
laws
of war, right? There are things that
we're all signitories to that you can
and can't do. Uh this this boat
situation is one. If you've launched a
strike and there are survivors who are
not able to participate in the fight,
you cannot kill them. Okay? If you don't
like the law, change the law. Don't just
pretend that you're the good guy so
everything's okay.
>> We're supposed to be a nation of laws. I
say this all the time. I want to get
back to something you said a second ago,
too. These terms, these terms are meant
to propagandize us. I remember in 200
five, 2004, 2005 um this term was just
suddenly introduced in the media. Uh the
term was Islamopfascism
[laughter] and do you remember this? And
then it turned out that it was created
by a PR firm for the Republican National
Committee and they tried hard to push
this term into regular daily usage,
Islamop fascism, and it just didn't
catch and then they just stopped using
it.
>> Yeah.
>> But it's it's all domestic propaganda.
All of it.
>> No, you could tell.
>> Narot terrorism.
>> Yeah. It reads something out of a um uh
you know like it's like you focus group
tested it like it's like like you were
just at a mall and some some mom was
like oo like Islamop fascism that sounds
scary. I don't want to be around those.
I don't you know like just I don't know
like just who were the monsters of the
20th century. Let's just let's just call
them Stalinist Hitler terrorists and
that'll that'll get everyone to shut up
and get on board with another
>> Oh my god. Yes. Oh yeah. That's it. All
right, guys. Let's take a moment and
thank our sponsor for today's show,
which is Moinkbox. I love this company,
a longtime sponsor of the Part of the
Problem podcast. MoBox are the great
defenders of American family farms and
the providers of delicious meat to good
Americans like you and me. If you're
anything like me, you're not really
comfortable with a lot of that meat
that's at the supermarket. It doesn't
taste great. You never know exactly
what's in it. With Moink, you know
you're getting delicious meat straight
from family farms right to your
doorstep. It's delivered right to you.
You don't got to drive and pick it up.
Everything you get is born, raised, and
harvested right here in the United
States of America. And I will tell you,
it is delicious. I've been ordering from
them for years. Delicious ground beef,
delicious steaks, delicious bacon,
delicious sausage, really, really good
stuff. So support American Family Farms
and join the Moink Movement today at
moinkbox.com/potp
right now and you will get free bacon
for a year. That's one year of the best
bacon you will ever taste, but for a
limited time only and only when you go
to minkbox.com/potpox.comp
for the best bacon you've ever had all
year long. All right, let's get back
into the show. Now, I did the the other
thing I wanted to make sure and
honestly, as I said to you before this,
I could I could talk to you for for 72
hours straight, so I but I won't I won't
do that. But I did want to ask about um
because I know you've you've discussed
kind of the um and this is something
like for people who read about this
stuff, this is very widely known for
many years, but this is something that I
think the American people really had no
idea about. And maybe a little bit over
the last two years because Israel's been
in the news so much, some people are
starting to learn about this. But the
the degree the hostility between like
Israeli intelligence and US intelligence
and the level of like spying that Israel
does on the United States of America,
you know, there's just I I it's an
interesting dynamic to me because
there's just like been like one story
after another um that over like recently
um things what I'm thinking about is
like the the Jonathan Pard uh story
where Huckabe is meeting with him at the
the embassy and like it's just Yeah. I
mean like it's just you just can't get
into how indefensible and outrageous
this stuff is. And then I the other
example that comes to mind is like the
um the uh when when they the Knesset had
that largely symbolic vote but still
they had this vote to annex the West
Bank which was Donald Trump's only
demand of them while JD Vance is in
Israel. They and you just had this
dynamic where there's a country who we
support who's essentially our welfare
country who we prop up yet turns around
and disrespects the United States of
America in this like egregious manner
and it's just too much to bear. But tell
people a little bit about this like what
were the relationships with MSAD in
those days and and Israeli
>> spying in general?
>> Yeah, I'll I'll give you my own little
thing on MSAD first then go to spying in
general. Um,
the CIA has always had just a terrible
relationship with Mossad. And it's
because Mossad actively spies on the
United States. The United States does
not spy on Israel. That's written in
stone. People poo poo this every time I
say it. I'm telling them it's written in
stone. The United States does not spy on
Israel. But Israel actively,
consistently has spied on the United
States. And it's not just Jonathan Pard.
There are lots of Jonathan Pards out
there. Um, in addition to that, and this
is just a a little story that I've I've
told before, I'll repeat to you. Uh,
dear friends of mine from the agency
whom I worked with very closely, sat
next to the husband, husband and wife
team. When I get transferred, well, no,
they get transferred to Jerusalem. Okay.
And they're declared to the Mossad,
meaning the station chief said, "These
are my officers. you know that they
belong to CIA. They're here to one one
is going to work for the uh State
Department in the embassy just doing
normal political work and the other's
going to go take Arabic lessons at the
university. Okay. So, no problem. Um
they go to a a dinner party at the
ambassador's residence one night and
they come home and all their living room
furniture has been rearranged.
Just like, haha, what are you going to
do about it? nothing. There's nothing
you can do about it. Well,
a year later, uh they uh go to the
ambassador's Christmas party. This is
when the embassy was in Tel Aviv. They
were assigned in Jerusalem. They go to
the Christmas party. They make the
45minut drive back to Jerusalem. And
people had taken shits in all of their
toilets and left them unflushed
just to show them we can come into your
home anytime we want and there's nothing
you can do about it. Their tour is up.
They're getting ready to leave. The
ambassador has a going away party for
them, which is completely normal.
And they go back home.
The dog is under the dining room table
whis whimpering.
somebody had cut its tail off and
wrapped the stump with gauze and medical
tape. Like, why? Why [__] with us like
that when we're your only lifeline,
right? We're your only friend at the
United Nations. We're giving you
billions of dollars of the Americans
taxpayers money so you can have your own
welfare state that we don't have here.
And then you're going to do that to our
officers who are there to help you, you
know, who are friendlies and they're
there to help you. Now, pard pard is
indicative of the broader problem. On my
very first day at the CIA as a new hire,
I was sitting in the auditorium with 300
other people and we got a briefing from
the CIA's director of security and he
told us that at the Israeli embassy in
Washington, there are two declared
intelligence officers, one from Mossad
and one from Shinbet. But the FBI had
identified
187 undeclared Israeli intelligence
officers spread all across the United
States, mostly trying to infiltrate
American defense contractors.
Why don't we arrest those 187 Israeli
spies? Because we have such a close
political relationship with Israel and
Congress wouldn't stand for it. But then
look at Pard. Pard was a Navy
intelligence officer who stole thousands
and thousands of pages of top secret not
not secret top secret documents that he
sold to Israel for money not for
ideology or because he was Jewish or
loved Israel. He did it for money and
then the Israelis traded those top
secret documents to the Soviet Union in
exchange for the release of Soviet Jews
to Israel.
Not only that, Pard got 30 years. He did
the whole 30. Benjamin Netanyahu on
literally every visit to the Oval Office
would say, no matter who president was,
release Pard. Release Pard. Release
Pard. And every president said no. Bill
Clinton almost said yes and George
Tennant said if you release Pard I will
resign and the head of every
intelligence agency in the American
government will will resign and so he
didn't do it. So Pard did all 30 of the
30 years went to Israel on a private jet
owned by Sheldon Adlesen. He was met at
the airport by Benjamin Netanyahu. He
got off the plane kissed the ground.
Netanyahu bestowed upon him Israeli
citizenship.
And then he gives a an interview to the
Israeli media, urging that Israel use
nuclear weapons on the United States if
the United States doesn't fall into
place for what Israel wants and urging
all American Jews with security
clearances to spy for Israel.
And so our ambassador meets with him in
the American embassy.
it I I'm befuddled by the whole
situation.
>> It's it's already it's so outrageous
just on the face of it. And then there's
the other I went on a whole rant about
this uh last week when the story came
out, but it's like if you understand
that like the giving secrets to the
Soviets at the height of the Cold War,
which is the entire justification for
the war in Korea, the war in Vietnam,
the the the um what you were just
talking about, the weapons to Iran, the
the the funding of the concistas in
Nicaragua, like the the whole national
emergency, the whole, as Will Buckley
said, creating a totalitarian
bureaucracy within our shores.
justified only by the Soviet menace. The
fact that spying for working with them,
giving them our top secret information
wouldn't have gotten Israel.
>> Maybe the debate should be between
banished forever and we go to war with
them, but like I mean the fact that we
would still continue supporting him
after that, it is just it is too it's
too crazy to possibly stand. And I think
that, you know, when when you lay it out
like that, you know, people talk about
this rise of anti-semitism
um online, and there is certainly some
of that, but it's like I think the
broader picture is what's happening here
is that that that type of relationship,
especially like it'd be one thing, John,
it'd be one thing if we were the
Palestinians and they were the Israelis.
Like if they had just conquered us and
it's like, well, this is what we live.
We live under Israeli control now. But
the thing is, we're the superpower.
We're the big giant country with the
biggest military and the biggest
economy. They're this tiny little
country. And the and it does seem when
you even ask the question, which I think
you as kind of as a rhetorical question,
but I got to say more and more I'm
looking for the real answer here. We go,
why were they doing this to our officers
over there? Why are they having this
vote um to to do the one thing Donald
Trump asked him not to do? The most
pro-Israel president of all time. The
one thing he said is you can't annex the
West Bank. So they vote to annex the
West Bank while his vice president
>> vice president's there
>> and and it does I don't want to be too
conspiratorial here but like the only
answer that I can think of is because
like yeah that's the point to let you
know to let you know that you are owned.
We don't actually care if public
opinion's turned against us. We don't
care if you know this. We want you CIA
officer to know that you don't actually
work for the bosses. We're the bosses
and you work for us and you will take it
because you have nothing else to do.
seems to me to be the only explanation.
>> Yeah. And you know, I I remember asking
at the time, "So, what do we do in a
case like that?" And one of the senior
officers said, "Well, we go and we say,
hey, cut it out. Come on. Why are you
harassing our people?" And they say,
"Oh, okay. Sorry. Okay." And then we're
good again for another year or two and
then they do it again.
>> It just makes no sense though, man. I
mean, do you do you have like um do you
think I mean your best guess I know I've
heard you talk about Epstein and stuff
like this before. Is it that like
obviously with Pard I I totally take
that um that explanation. Yeah, people
do things for money especially huge sums
of money for sure. Yeah. But like so is
that is it just a mix of people being
some of them are blackmailed, some of
them are bribed, some of them just face
the political pressure of the lobby and
stuff like that. Some of them have their
religious convictions. Is that just what
you your assessment of it is?
>> No. Counter intelligence officials will
tell you that for 85% it's the money.
This is just a cash deal. It's all about
the money. A handful are going to do it
for ideological reasons. A handful are
going to do it for for revenge. Maybe
they've been passed over for promotion.
They hate their boss. They're they're
angry at the government. Whatever. But
for the most part, it's this is a cash
transaction.
>> Yeah. Well, I think doesn't that kind of
describe all of it too though in a way
like there are ideologues all around.
But what's really going on is it's
business. It's all like all the wars.
It's big business. And that's really,
you know, cuz like even and I and I
think sometimes maybe I get too caught
up in kind of like the ideological
worldview of say the neoconservatives
where it's like look it is true that
they had this ideological worldview but
why were all those weapons companies
pouring money into their think tanks?
Not because they agreed with them, not
because they cared about.
>> No, not at all. I say all the time, it's
not an accident that before 9/11, the
highest concentration of millionaires in
America per capita was in Silicon Valley
and after 9/11, it's in Washington DC.
>> Yeah.
>> It's not an accident.
>> Yeah. Where where they produce nothing
except weapons of war. [laughter]
Nothing is actually built except that.
Well, uh sir, I I knew I would really
enjoy talking with you and I really did.
Uh I would love to do this I would love
to do this again sometime soon. Um,
please let everybody know where they can
find your stuff, where they can learn
more about the stuff you're talking
about.
>> Oh, thank you. Thank you. I'm like all
over YouTube now. I actually have two uh
I have two podcasts on YouTube. One is
called Deep Program. I do it every
morning uh from 9 to 10 with Ted R.
There's a there's a more like
intellectual one that I do once a week
called Deep Focus, also on YouTube. And
then I've got a kind of a fun podcast on
Apple podcast called uh uh Deadrop What
makes a spy tick and we talk about all
these kinds of issues. Uh that's right
now it's only on uh Apple podcasts and
I'm on X and Insta and Facebook and all
the usual places.
>> Awesome. Well, yes, you are you are all
over Twitter these days. I see what my
my algorithm I can't go 5 seconds
without seeing another one of your
videos, but they're always great. So,
I'm great. I'm grateful that the
algorithm is working on our side. John
Kuryaku, thank you so much for taking
the time. Uh, thank you everybody for
listening. We'll catch you next time.